OK.
We are just starting the meeting.
I'm going to go ahead and admit everyone.
I'll just take a second here.
All right.
Looks like everybody who was in the
lobbyist in and so we should be good to
go.
OK.
Thank you, Johnny.
Good morning, everybody.
This is Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health.
I'm the Director for the Center for
Medical Cannabis and Psilocybin,
and this is the Patient Qualification and
Safety Committee for the Medical
Psilocybin Advisory Board.
And the Chair is Ian Dunn.
And so I will turn this meeting on over
to Ian.
But just a reminder real quick,
we do have cameras off and we do have
everybody starting out as being muted.
And so I do want to remind everyone we do
put these recordings up online so they
are accessible to the public.
And so please watch your language and
ensure that you are utilizing appropriate
language to be for us to be able to post
this publicly.
That is also one of the reasons why we do
not have cameras on just in the case
there is something in the background to
make sure that we don't have to try to go
back later and blur and bleep things.
So thank you everybody.
I appreciate it.
And again I will turn this on over to the
chair, Ian Dunn.
Ian, it is your meeting.
Perfect.
Good morning everyone.
Welcome to the Patient Qualification and
Safety committee.
Today we are going to do a quick
procedural motion to adopt the final
first part of our committee deliverable.
This will be all of our recommendations
regarding patient qualification and
safety and then we will go ahead and move
on to working on our second committee
deliverable,
which will be additional qualifying
conditions before we begin accepting
petitions.
So we will go ahead and begin with the
consolidated recommendations.
I do want to notify everyone this was
sent out to the committee members,
but there was one change made.
All of the references to the word guide
were changed to facilitator.
That was just a more agreed upon term
that we had found in other committees.
So that was the only change that was made
at this time.
I will hear any objections to adopting
our first committee to deliverable.
All right.
And I see Eileen's hand up.
All right, Eileen Brewer,
I have in wait a minute.
Let's see.
OK, there we go.
I have enabled your mic.
Hey, good morning.
Thank you so much.
In the section on these recommendations
regarding exclusions,
the the ones that you know really are
recommended that they can never receive
services even with advanced monitoring.
It it states that any medical conditions
that are resolved can be re evaluated
that are marked resolved by a doctor,
but it doesn't say anything about
psychiatric conditions that are resolved.
You have borderline personality disorder
listed here and my understanding is that
90% of borderline personality cases do
resolve within 10 years.
So I would think that like,
this is a psychiatric condition and not a
medical condition,
but you're saying that they never have
the opportunity to use these services
even if their condition is resolved.
So I was wondering why that was and if
that could be updated.
Thanks.
I have never heard of borderline
personality disorder being marked
resolved.
It could be marked, treated with,
you know, depending on the person,
there's a number of different medications
because there's not a specific outline.
But in terms of like resolved as in a
cure,
I have never heard of borderline
personality disorder being cured, Carly.
All right, Carly, can you hear me?
Yep, great.
I don't have personal experience with
borderline personality disorder,
but I will say that there are plenty of
disorders, diseases,
conditions that are today uncurable,
but that doesn't mean that people have
not been cured.
I have a traumatic brain injury,
which is considered a chronic condition
by the Centers for Medicaid and Medicare
Services.
But I've done experimental treatments,
treatments in other countries.
And I basically consider myself cured,
even though it doesn't seem the
literature like that's possible.
So I would like to echo that there should
be some room for a possibility for for,
you know, people to become eligible again.
All right.
And next we've got Kay Hawk.
Ian.
Ian, you were on mute.
Oh, perfect.
I was just calling up Kay Hawk.
So no worries.
OK.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Good morning, everybody.
Yeah, having worked with people,
including people with all kinds of
diagnosis,
diagnosis is just not an exact science.
So people can get stuck with a diagnosis
that may or may not even be accurate in
the 1st place.
And I don't know anything that is really,
really incurable.
You know,
there's things that are unlikely or more
difficult,
but I wouldn't say anything is incurable
under the right conditions.
So I'm I'm glad we have some
acknowledgement about that,
that things can change.
All right, And then Gregory Evans,
good morning.
It sounds like we're just like going
right into it.
I want to make sure that we have an
understanding that these blocking like
the what, what's the term and whatever,
like the conditions that prevent
treatment are future proof like I, I like,
I understand that this stuff can and will
change,
especially as we adopt new qualifying
conditions,
which we'll discuss later today.
But BPD and things in that zone are so
have historically been so commonly
misdiagnosed.
I think that creating a permanent block
for somebody who doesn't like,
I want to allow for the ability for
somebody to find a doctor that really
understands them and perhaps heal from
some of that negative psychological
trauma,
like psychological trauma from
psychological care that they've received
in the past by getting into true
alignment with their practitioners and
their care team.
When somebody where somebody may be
misdiagnosed as BPD and really they just
are severely traumatized,
that is something that this medicine is
specifically designed to help with.
And I understand that going in on our
first phase,
we want to be really careful about like
how successful we are and, and, and,
and by like constraining some of the
treatments, we can do that.
We can like put this in a very safe
container.
I just want to make sure that it is
future proof and the the people in this
room can understand and trust that this
is not concrete.
This is all exploration and, and,
and has plasticity.
How's that?
Yeah, no.
And I've never I if you guys would like
to move it to tier 3.
The reason why it was in Tier 4 was we
worried about causing emotional
instability for a duration of longer than
the treatment.
I know that there are some studies that
are looking into BPD and psilocybin used
for BPD.
Their own reason it's included as of now
is because there is evidence stating that
we could cause emotional dysregulation
and that's what that was there to prevent
in the that we discussed in the other.
It's not necessarily saying like we can't,
but maybe there's maybe there's a way to
like put a general clause that
reclassification of previous diagnosis
can be modified by qualified whatever,
like however we define who can change a
designation on a person's psychological
chart.
I guess I don't know, just a thought,
right?
And I think too,
this would probably serve more as
guidance, not necessarily a rule,
but I think Dominic has a better
clarification for that.
Thank you.
Yeah, good morning, everybody.
And Ian,
you actually just you just hit upon the
point that I was going to mention is
remember that these aspects as far as
around the different conditions
themselves are part of the guidance
documents, not a part of the rule.
And So what the rule will consist of is
just sort of what information that the
clinician is going to have to provide to
demonstrate that the individual does meet
the criteria of whatever condition we're
looking at,
whether it's one of the initial 4 or
conditions even in the future.
And so for example,
if you know with regard to, you know,
treatment resistant depression that it's
the clinician is then attesting that this
individual,
that this patient has treatment resistant
depression,
that they have gone through the
appropriate testing to ensure that that
is indeed the situation.
And that they believe that as they have
done their own and additional research
and looking at the guidance that will be
provided through some of these other
documents that they then believe that
that utilizing psilocybin has the
potential to be more beneficial rather
than negative effects for the patient and
their condition.
And so remember, these are about guidance.
So as far As for this, this aspect,
this is not a set in stone.
Guidance is set to be reviewed on a
regular basis.
There hasn't been a timeline set for that
at this point.
That may be something that would help
with regard to some of these concerns and
questions is to say maybe,
and it doesn't necessarily have to happen
in here,
but to potentially say these guidance
will be reviewed, you know,
by this committee,
under Advisory Board in the department,
you know, once every two years,
once every year,
whatever seems appropriate and to also
look at that.
So that's one of the other aspects I just
want to bring up and re and remind
everyone this is about guidance.
This portion is not necessarily set in
stone.
Thank you.
And I think that's I think that's the
voice that we needed to hear this morning
regarding like the framing of this.
And I think how we communicate that
outwardly is very important.
So thank you.
Yeah.
And then I do also want to add so I in
that conditions line it had said
reassessment may occur for medical
conditions that have demonstrably
resolved and for which documentation
supports sustained clinical stability.
So if you've had it resolved or it was a
misdiagnosis or whatever,
and you've shown, you know,
I've actually just had, you know,
depression and they or ADHD and they
diagnosed me as bipolar or whatever the
situation was, it would allow for that.
I went ahead and clarified it and said
reassessment may occur for medical and
mental health conditions that have
demonstrably resolved,
just to add that extra clarification.
Yeah.
All right.
Are there any other objections in this?
Let's see.
I think Eileen's hand is still up.
Eileen, did you?
Oh, OK.
Yeah.
I mean,
what Gregory said is really what I was,
what I was asking for initially.
And I,
I just wanted to reflect people's
concerns that like people can be
misdiagnosed and especially for
psychiatric conditions where there's no
like blood test you can take to find out
if you have borderline personality
disorder or any psychiatric condition,
you know,
it's frequent for people to get
misdiagnosed.
So I think that that helps a lot.
I do want everything I want to say, sorry,
I said,
I do want to recognize I have been
misdiagnosed.
I know that sometimes we do need to
resolve it.
So definitely,
I recognize that and I'm sorry if I was
trying if I implied in any way that like,
I don't respect that.
I definitely do,
especially for mental health conditions
where oftentimes the diagnosis is based
on subjective data.
And then how the patient responds to
treatment is also a big factor that's
used.
So it can really be a,
a guess and check game, right?
And,
and that is why borderline personality
disorder is resolved like 90% of the time
because it's misdiagnosed a lot.
But the other thing that I want to say
about guidance as opposed to like,
you know,
rules is that guidance gets put out all
the time for things and people follow
that, especially in a space like this.
If you look at the guidance that was put
out for opiate prescribing,
that is just guidance.
It's not rules.
Every single doctor in the country pretty
much follows that guidance without being
flexible at all because they are afraid
of repercussions.
And I imagine that in a space like
psilocybin,
people are going to follow the guidance
rigorously to the letter as they
interpret it because they are afraid of
repercussions from boards that would give
them licenses.
So even though we're saying this is just
guidance and it's going to be reviewed
and we don't know how often it's going to
be reviewed and we don't have that yet,
I would caution people to understand that
guidance is is still going to be
considered rules by most people.
Thank you.
Alrighty, thank you.
And then any objections at this time to
the amended version?
I'll go ahead and post it in the chat.
And then, Jorge,
you're showing the major depressive
disorder document and not the
consolidated recommendations.
I will switch that right now.
OK.
Is there a page you want me to scroll to
depending on what we end up at?
All right.
And then at this time,
I'll go ahead and ask for a unanimous
consent motion.
If you have an objection to this,
please raise your hand at this time.
K Hawk.
Do you have something to say?
I'm sorry,
that was just a technical glitch.
No worries, Chris.
So I'm curious.
Good morning, everyone.
I'm curious which one of these documents
are representing rules that we're
implementing and which ones represent
guidance.
So rules would be like in relation to
licensure or fixed things that are in
place.
Typically guidance is reserved for how
the care is presented,
the stability and that kind of thing.
I think Dominic could provide better
explanation than I could.
But yeah,
what I would actually say is that these
are guidance,
that these documents are all guidance
documents,
not rule based or not to be rule.
Cool.
And then I see Carly.
I was wondering how the last bullet point,
active inability to provide informed
consent would be defined.
I represent the brain injury community
and I fear that people could say that, oh,
you have a brain injury,
you can't consent to this,
or you have a stroke,
you just had a stroke,
something like that,
when this medicine could be really,
really helpful for those people.
So an active inability to provide
informed consent would be things like
severely progressed Alzheimer's or
dementia.
It could be active intoxication.
It could be a manic episode.
But that inability to provide informed
consent, if it can mean a lot of things,
it just means that you have to be
functionally aware of what you are
accepting.
We don't want to send someone into a
psychedelic trip if they don't want to.
Oh yeah.
So if they say I want to do this,
I agree that works right?
If they can understand what they are
being offered, yeah, and warned about,
and then they say, yeah, I agree,
then that would be fine.
OK, cool, Sky.
OK, sorry.
I had my probiads on.
If a clinician recommends this program,
then the the clinician would have made
that determination correct.
This is Sky Rivers.
I'm with the Santa Fe reporter.
Just putting it out there.
So am I correct in that?
It would usually be the facilitator
because they're the ones that are
accepting that informed consent form.
So if they came into, for instance,
an administration session intoxicated,
even if the clinician said yeah,
they're good,
we would still say they have an inability
to provide informed consent to that
psilocybin process.
I think for me,
I am someone who does suffer from TBI,
fell down a flight of stairs in a manhole,
hit my head, but I'm aware of everything.
I don't have it to the degree where I
don't understand what's going on,
obviously.
But for someone like me who has traumatic
brain injury and wants to go into the
program, if the clinician says it's OK,
then there are different levels,
as I think Carly was Speaking of that,
that occurs.
So that's where I just wanted the
clarification.
So if the clinician says, OK,
they have TBI, but it's a mild or,
you know, 1 to 4 levels,
I don't know how you want to work that
out if you're going to put that in there.
My,
my question would be again on this
subject,
would the clinician who's recommending it,
who knows the patient be a, you know,
be the source instead of the facilitator
making the determination when the Doctor
Who has been seeing this patient for
years is saying they're fine,
they're good for the,
I think it has to do with the reason they
would have an inability.
So if it was like your instance and we
were referring to a a historical
diagnosis,
then we would refer to that the provider
that has been treating that for the
longest duration.
Yeah.
But if it was like a current thing,
I smell alcohol on their breath,
that's where it would be that kind of
that guide.
Each clinical role that we worked out in
dosage has clinical practice and scope.
So it would not be within a facilitator
scope to say actually I'm going to
override a clinical decision made by the
clinician or the psychedelic therapist.
It would be on the original referring
when it's a historical diagnosis.
They each have their own little role,
right.
And then quickly you brought up twice
about, you know, smelling of alcohol.
Are we comparing someone who has an
addiction to someone who has traumatic
brain injury, though?
Someone who is sick,
regardless of pain or TBI might come in
with alcohol.
I don't know, you know,
or pain medication.
No, I'm,
I'm comparing 2 instances of inability to
provide informed consent.
Oh, OK.
All right.
That's all.
I just want a clarification.
Thank you, Ann, Of course.
And then Gregory, hey,
I think you covered most of it,
but I just wanted to try to clarify it
just in very simple terms for Sky 'cause
I think this is a,
it's one of those things that's that's
easy to misunderstand.
And it's also like in progress like this
has not like these, this is still gelling.
But like Ian said,
there's different types of practitioners.
They each have their own scope and role.
There's a,
there you go to one person that says
you're good to go clearance,
that person's probably going to clear you
based on conditions when you get to the
facilitation session.
There's, there are,
there are layers of consent through the
entire process.
And if you come in in a state that is not
acceptable per the guidelines of the
program to receive treatment,
that's another like time that that can be
assessed.
But that that the facilitator in the
session is not going to be judging your
mental like overall mental conditions.
You've already been cleared for the
program.
You've been through preparatory sessions,
you're showing up for the day.
But if you're drunk,
that might pause the session.
That I think that it let me know if I got
that correct.
Ian, that is exactly right.
Alrighty,
any other points clarifications we can
make cool,
then we will go ahead and move to a vote.
All those in favor of adopting the
committee consolidated recommendations,
please raise your hand at this time.
Looks like a show of four hands.
All of those opposed.
I don't see any perfect with four yeses 0
Nos.
The motion passed.
Now we can get on to the fun part of
today's meeting.
So over the last meeting we decided to
discuss depression and we decided to
discuss neurological neurological
disorders.
So to best encapsulate at least two of
the neurological disorders we talked
about were Alzheimer's and Parkinson's.
So I think both of those would fit within
the definition of existential distress
due to a life limiting illness.
So if Jorge,
you could bring that up for me and then
two others that we discussed that we will
go into later today are chronic headaches
was the other neurological condition.
But for the first two we did Alzheimer's
and Parkinson's.
Go ahead and put that in the chat.
So we'll go ahead and read this as well.
Whereas existential distress associated
with a life limiting illness is a serious
form of psychological, emotional,
and spiritual suffering that may include
death, anxiety, demoralization,
hopelessness, loss of meaning,
loss of dignity,
grief related to functional decline,
and difficulty adjusting to serious or
progressive illness.
And whereas existential distress is
common among patients with life
threatening or life limiting medical
conditions and may substantially impair
quality of life, emotional well-being,
treatment, engagement,
family relationships,
and end of life adjustment.
And whereas existential distress is not
always adequately captured by traditional
psychiatric diagnosis alone,
AS patients may experience clinically
significant suffering related to
mortality, identity, autonomy, meaning,
and anticipated loss even when they do
not meet the full diagnostic criteria for
major depressive disorder,
generalized anxiety disorder,
or post traumatic stress disorder.
And whereas standard palliative,
psychiatric and psychotherapeutic
interventions may not adequately relieve
existential distress for all patients,
particularly when distress is related to
loss of meaning of life, fear of death,
demoralization,
or spiritual suffering in the context of
life limiting illness.
And whereas randomized clinical part
trials in patients with life threatening
cancer have demonstrated that psilocybin
assisted psychotherapy can produce rapid,
clinically meaningful and sustained
reductions in anxiety,
depression and cancer related
psychological distress when administered
in a structured therapeutic setting with
preparation,
monitored administration and integration
support.
And whereas in a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled crossover trial at
John Hopkins University involving
patients with life threatening cancer,
psilocybin produced substantial and
sustained decreases in depressed mood and
anxiety along with improvements in
quality of life, life meaning, death,
acceptance, and optimism,
with effects persisting at six months
follow up in substantial proportion of
participants.
Whereas in a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled crossover trial at New
York University involving patients with
cancer related anxiety, depression,
and psilocybin assisted psychotherapy
produced immediate,
substantial and sustained improvements in
anxiety and depression with additional
improvements in existential distress,
quality of life and spiritual well-being,
and attitudes towards death.
And whereas long term follow up of the
New York University trial found that
reductions in cancer related psychiatric
and existential distress we're sustained
approximately 3.2 to 4.
5 years after psilocybin assisted
psychotherapy,
suggesting potential durability of
benefit in appropriately supported
patients.
Whereas,
secondary analysis of psilocybin assisted
psychotherapy and cancer related distress
have demonstrated acute and sustained
reduction and loss of meaning,
hopelessness, demoralization,
and death anxiety,
supporting the relevance of psilocybin
assisted therapy to existential distress
specifically,
rather than depressive or anxious
symptoms alone.
And WHEREAS recent reviews of psilocybin
assisted therapy for existential distress
and serious illness conclude that the
available evidence is promising,
particularly in cancer and palliative
care populations,
while also emphasizing the need for
larger randomized trials and careful
clinical safeguards.
And WHEREAS the inclusion of existential
distress associated with life limiting
illness recognizes a legitimate and
clinically significant form of suffering
that may arise in the context of serious
illness and may warrant access to
regulated psilocybin services where
clinically appropriate.
Therefore,
the committee finds that the current body
of clinical,
systematic and mechanistic evidence
supports the inclusion of existential
distress associated with the life
limiting illness as a qualification
within a regulated evidence based
psilocybin program for the purposes of
eligibility.
Existential distress associated with a
life limiting illness means clinically
significant psychological,
emotional or spiritual distress arising
in the context of a serious,
progressive or life limiting in medical
condition,
including but not limited to death
anxiety, demoralization, hopelessness,
loss of meaning, loss of dignity,
grief related to functional decline or
adjustment related suffering.
That was a lot, all right.
So any discussion, questions, comments,
concerns?
Eileen, I'm always first.
I feel like I'm like the person who
complaints a lot and and I don't want to
because this is this is phenomenally good
and I I love it.
However,
I do have concerns that it doesn't encap
encapsulate all of the Parkinson's
patients that you would want.
The reason that we're talking about
Parkinson's at all is because there was a
study done last year at UCSF for it was
it was a small study of Parkinson's
patients and the results were profound.
And they did find that they were looking
at existential distress with Parkinson's
and they did find that it helped.
They also found that it helped with mood,
cognition and motor function.
And so,
so those results suggested that this
could be the the first study that showed
that psilocybin could help with
neurodegenerative disease as far as
helping to repair the brain.
And so if we get to the point where we
find that if we're just talking about
existential distress and not calling out,
you know,
somebody with early stage Parkinson's
disease who does not yet have that
existential distress,
they may not be included as we would like
them to be.
Obviously, this is early stage work.
But if we are talking about neurological
diseases,
we want to consider that it's not just
existential distress associated with
neurological conditions that make
psilocybin appropriate for these patients.
Thank you.
And I do recognize that existential
distress is not the primary reason and
the new evidence is astonishing.
My thing is,
is if we try to send that over right now,
I don't think the body of evidence is
sufficient to just say on its own,
Parkinson's is qualifying,
but there is substantial evidence on
existential distress.
So this may be not while we can't approve
Parkinson's today, right,
we don't have the the evidence for it.
We can approve the existential distress
associated with Parkinson's and kind of
allow that to be an option for the
provider and they can explain those
benefits to the patient.
Does that make sense?
And then Gregory, hi,
this is a great crosswalk moment.
The research and continuous improvement
committee is already like opening up the
conversation for like what we look at for
next phases.
And it is really,
it is really a very difficult to decision
for me to like let this go because I
think TBI neurological disorders are the
highest like value grabs for actual
pharmacological impact of psilocybin 5
meo and other HD 2A related compounds.
But the way I'm seeing this, Ian,
is and what you're saying is like,
let's create this little loophole where
people with existential distress can
start to like maybe get into some of
those earlier phases while in like our
phase two and our Phase 3 will come with
deeper arguments for like actual medical
treatments for neurological disorders.
Is that kind of the way that you're
framing this?
Yeah, excellent.
Is there is not enough randomized
clinical data.
But if we begin this program and we begin
treating Parkinson's patients with the
existential distress and we can show our
own state numbers that show that it is
greatly improving motor function,
that we would be on a much better path to
submit 'cause we'll stop to submit it to
the Department of Health as a qualifying
condition.
We'll have a much better basis than if we
just try to submit it now as just
Parkinson's.
Yeah.
And I think I think the work that we can
do in racy committee to like prep those
conversations could be really informative
for those like future conversations.
I would want to just I do want to just
plug found a new company that should be
watched in this space.
It's a company called 5 discovery Doctor
Manesh Girm is the one of the main Co
founders and they're utilizing A
synthetic modification of five Mel to
treat specifically neurological disorders.
But I think that the the parallel
psilocybin research could be extremely
valuable for like hand in hand discovery.
Anyways, I like I,
I'm cool with this the way it is,
but I think it's just important to
understand that it's like definitely this
stuff is not in phase one.
But it I like that it that there's a
little kind of back door if that's OK to
say.
Yeah, it allows us to use,
it allows us to prove,
to create an evidence based program.
While the evidence for Parkinson's is
still developing,
at least if they are suffering with
existential distress,
we can ensure that they still get
treatment.
Yeah, I, I also can we put, can we note,
can we speak TBI in that as well?
Can we make sure that ends up in the
language TBI would be accepted?
So the language does not list a specific
condition.
It just says clinically significant
psychological,
emotional or spiritual distress arising
in the context of serious progressive or
life limiting medical condition.
So it could be related to death anxiety.
It could be related to just, you know,
if you've ever gotten diagnosed with the
something later in life,
you definitely know the anxiety.
But yeah, no, this would perfect if TBI,
if a TBI patient had existential distress,
they would also qualify under this.
While the research is churning, right?
Any more questions, comments, concerns,
Harley, I think it's great.
I think it can include being anyone with
a neurological condition or even like
Lyme's disease, arthritis,
lots of different things that are chronic
and distressing and existential.
So I just wanted to say I think this is
great.
Thank you.
Perfect.
Well, thank you for that.
All right,
then let's go ahead and take a vote on
existential distress associated with a
life limiting illness.
Please raise your hand at this time to
adopt.
I do see teeth and hands again.
Perfect.
And please lower your hands at this time.
All right.
And then those opposed,
please raise your hand 10 yeses,
this is adopted.
Let's go ahead and move on to bluster
headaches,
honestly probably set it under that as
well.
But there is a good amount of evidence
for this one, so I'm opening that now.
Gregory,
I was just curious if you could speak to
why you didn't include what's that other
word like the other kind of headaches,
not cluster headaches, the migraine,
migraine.
Yeah, migraines.
Why did we not include that that language
in here and just have clusters?
Curious.
Honestly,
the studies I were reading just listed
them primarily as cluster headaches.
So that's just what I had done.
And because in the last meeting we had
brought up a bunch of conditions and so I
had a list of what I was checking off
under neurological for the next 1.
So it was already on my list.
We can add migraines.
I, I really don't know.
I don't have like a hard stance on it,
but it's funny 'cause it's like on,
it's one of those things that we really
just don't understand.
Like is it a neurological disorder or is
it not?
You know,
when you get really deep into it,
there is a big question mark.
So I have heard some anecdotal reports of
like positive effects for migraines,
but also like I haven't seen like any
extensive studies.
I think studies are a little bit it's
hard one to to hit.
I don't.
I mean is there a difference between
cluster headaches and migraines without
aura?
Yes, 100%.
Cluster headache and migraine are two
completely different disorders.
There's about 100 different headache
diagnosis.
Cluster headache and migraine are two of
the two of the the primary headache
disorders.
Cluster headache has different symptoms,
different classification.
It is.
It is a completely different disease.
There are completed phase one studies for
cluster headache.
I'm not sure if the migraine study that
was done at Yale is was phase one or just
a pilot study.
I think it had about 50 patients.
But there is more anecdotal and
researched evidence for cluster headache
than there is for migraine at this time.
I personally know about 1000 people who
have taken psilocybin for cluster
headache and are doing very well.
So in response to that,
thank you for that clarification.
So I have found a good number of studies
on cluster headaches.
So if we want to go ahead and go through
this,
whereas or Gregory had a point before,
I just go ahead and read.
Oh,
I don't think my hand was just still up.
I'm,
I'm looking to see if that Yale research
moved to phase,
but I'll post it in the chat.
All right.
So,
WHEREAS cluster headache is a primary
headache disorder characterized by
excruciating unilateral pain and
autonomic symptoms,
often referred to as suicide headaches
due to the severity of the attacks in the
high rate of patient distress.
And whereas,
current steadative care treatments
including high flow oxygen triptans and
prophylactic agents like verapamil and
lithium are insufficient,
contraindicated or associated with
significant side effects for many
patients.
And whereas preliminary survey data first
identified A specialized pulse dosing
protocols,
subalucinogenic or low dose psilocybin as
an effective method for terminating
cluster periods and extending remission.
And whereas follow up large scale user
surveys confirm that patients reported
psilocybin to be more effective than
conventional treatments for both aborting
individual attacks and preventing future
cycles.
WHEREAS, double-blind,
placebo-controlled pilot studies have
demonstrated that oral psilocybin
significantly reduces the weekly
frequency of clusters attacks compared to
placebo,
with the benefits persisting for weeks
after only a few doses.
And WHEREAS,
subsequent clinical research has further
characterized the dose relation response
relationship,
suggesting that the therapeutic effect on
headache frequency may be distinct from
the acute psychedelic or mystical
experience.
And.
Whereas,
longitudinal neuroimaging and five HT 2A
receptor occupancy studies provide a
neurobiological framework for how many
psilocybin may reset the trigeminal
autonomic reflex through modulation of
the hypothalamus and tone and system.
And whereas the accumulated clinical
signals and safety profiles from these
trials indicate a low risk of serious
adverse events where administrated,
administered in controlled or monitored
settings.
Therefore,
the committee finds that the current body
of clinical,
systematic and mechanistic evidence
supports the conclusion of cluster
headaches as a qualifying condition with
an irregular regulated evidence based
psilocybin services program with the
references below.
Questions.
Comments.
Concerns.
I think this is amazing and I really
appreciate it.
I don't know how we we managed to do this.
I know that it's going to be something
for the different committee than this,
but I do want to caution that treating
cluster headache is very different than
treating a psychiatric condition because
the dosing needs to be more frequent,
except it's lower dosing usually.
So I don't know how we go about
communicating with other committees that
hey,
this is something that we're recommending,
but there needs to be training around it
so that people aren't treated
inappropriately and then think it doesn't
work for them.
That's my only caution.
Thanks.
Thank you, Gregory.
I just wanted to augment that last
comment because like this is something
that we're going to see when we get into
medical treatments for pain where,
you know,
patients are going to need one or two
grand like, oh,
I got a significant dose like every
couple days for a period of time based on
the research.
And it's like not really something that
the format of this program can handle,
but I think it it is something to be
considered about like safety and
containers of use and home use and like
stuff like that that we haven't really
been able to get into.
And I don't think we will get into in
this first phase.
But like, man,
that's a fun one to untangle.
But yeah, it will,
I definitely have some ideas and we'll
we'll get into that more in the other
committees.
But yeah, no,
that will be an interesting problem to
solve.
Questions, comments,
concerns on cluster headaches.
And then thank you, Gregory,
for putting those migraine studies.
I will review them and then prepare a
migraine document for the next meeting.
All right, with no further discussion,
we will go ahead and vote on cluster
headaches.
All those in favor,
please raise your hand.
I see eight hands up.
All right, please lower your hands.
And then all those against,
please raise your hand.
I see zero hands raised.
Perfect.
All righty, Jorge.
Now the document you've been waiting for
since the beginning.
Major depressive disorder.
OK, All righty.
So well,
I understand in phase one we're gonna
work with the legislative conditions and
so that means allowing treatment
resistant patients to go first.
I personally am not a big fan of forcing
patients to go through classical
pharmacological treatments,
especially when the evidence says that
depression doesn't just if they haven't
only evaluated treatment resistant
depression,
they've also evaluated major depressive
disorders.
So I think this would be something that
we could look into.
So whereas major depressive disorder is a
prevalent,
recurrent and potentially life
threatening psychiatric condition
associated with substantial functional
impairment,
diminished quality of life and elevated
risk of suicide and remains the leading
cause of disability worldwide.
And whereas standard treatments for MDD
include antidepressant pharmacotherapy
and psychotherapy are limited by delayed
onset of action in complete response,
adverse effects,
and high rates of treatment resistance,
leaving a significant proportion of
individuals with persistent or
debilitating depressive symptoms.
And whereas high quality randomized
clinical trials demonstrate that
psilocybin assisted therapy produces
rapid, clinically meaningful,
and sustained reductions in depressive
symptoms when administered within a
structured therapeutic setting that
includes psychological preparation and
integration.
And whereas in a multi site, double-blind,
active, placebo-controlled,
phase two randomized clinical trial
involving adults with major depressive
disorder,
a single 25 milligram dose of psilocybin
was associated with a large and
statistically significant reduction in
the Montgomery Asperger Depression Rating
Scale scores compared with niacin,
with antidepressant effects evident by
day 8 and sustained through six weeks,
accompanied by significant improvement in
functional disability and no serious
treatment emergence adverse effects.
WHEREAS,
these findings are consistent with an
earlier randomized clinical or earlier
randomized controlled evidence from a
trial conducted at John Hopkins
University in which two psilocybin
sessions combined with supportive
psychotherapy produced large,
very large effect sizes,
rapid symptom reduction,
and high rates of clinical responses and
remission at one month follow up in
adults with major depressive disorder.
And whereas converging pharmacological
and translational evidence indicates that
psilocybin acts as a rapid acting
antidepressant through serotonergic 5 HT
2A receptor agonism and downstream
neuroplastic mechanisms including the
modulation of glutaminergic signaling,
synaptogenesis and brain derived
neurotropic factor related pathways.
Providing a biologically plausible
explanation for the rapid onset and
durability of antidepressant effects
observed in clinical trials.
And whereas the magnitude,
rapid onset and durability of
antidepressant effects observed with
psilocybin assisted therapy compare
favorably to existing pharmacological
treatments for MDD.
Therefore,
the committee finds that the current body
of clinical,
systematic and mechanistic evidence
supports the inclusion of major
depressive disorder as a qualifying
condition within a regulated evidence
based psilocybin program.
We made it guys.
So questions, comments, concerns,
discussion.
Yeah,
I figured this would be the most pretty
easy to agree on.
But Carly,
so this doesn't require someone to go
through many rounds of antidepressants
and things that fail at those first.
Is that correct?
No.
Wonderful, Gregory.
Just *******.
Oh, gosh Dang it.
Bravo, is all I was gonna say.
Well written.
Thank you.
And I'm sorry.
It's OK.
It happens.
The best of us.
Alrighty.
All those in favor of adopting major
depressive disorder,
please raise your hand at this time.
I see.
Seven hands raised.
Seven.
Yes.
All right.
Please lower your hands at this time.
All right, all those opposed,
please raise your hands.
I see no hands raised.
Perfect.
Major depressive disorder is past and
those are the three conditions that I had
prepared for today.
So what do you guys want to discuss next
time?
Could you fill me in?
I was invited to this from by Bob from
Cluster Busters.
And I just would love to hear some
context like what are these meetings?
What are we trying to do?
I just kind of came in and gave my
opinions.
But yeah,
your question you just asked like,
can you prime me please?
Yeah.
So we are the Patient Qualification and
Safety Committee.
All of the committees work with the
Medical Psilocybin Advisory Board to
allow more community input from people
around the state of New Mexico and the
development of this program.
I said since the beginning,
we have 7 very smart board members,
but they will never compete with the
intelligence of the entire state of New
Mexico.
So I've always opened these meetings up
to the public and allowed public
participation.
In regards to my specific question,
I was just asking what other qualifying
conditions do you think we should discuss?
Have you know,
considered what would you like me to look
into?
I know we brought in brought up migraines
during the meeting,
so we can definitely look at that.
Just kind of hearing from the community
and then your you take the, the,
the considerations of the community to
the New Mexico Department of Health
psilocybin Committee.
So I'll take all of the so I'll take
committee recommendations.
The committee recommendations go to the
Medical Psilocybin Advisory Board.
We'll discuss them.
If they agree,
they get sent to the Department of Health.
If they do not agree,
they get sent back down to committee so
that we can make whatever changes that we
need to and then we go from there.
OK, awesome.
Thanks so much.
Perfect.
Thank you for joining us, Gregory.
Oh yeah.
Thank you Carly for showing up.
I think that the the communities that you
represent are under represented in these
meetings.
So I'm really happy to see you here.
As far as things that we could get into,
like and to clarify,
we're probably looking at like year plus
out for any action on on these things,
if I'm not mistaken, right?
Like we're not like we're pretty set for
what's happening in December, right?
But I think digging into the guts of Sud
and PTSD and then seeing how we can fold
in complex PTSD could be pretty
interesting and combined treatments for
multiple disorders.
And then the the other stuff that sits on
my radar would be chronic pain,
as I think pain management is hugely
important, understudied,
definitely something that we could open
some doors on potentially OCD and eating
disorders are also kind of on my tag list.
All right, well,
I definitely know we can get started on
migraines, PTSD and C PTSD.
It would depend on how the department
defined it.
But usually, like in the DSM 5,
they're the same.
I know, I know I'm popular.
I don't agree with the DSM five.
I'm just saying, did they not?
I thought they just changed it.
Did they just change it?
Well, I mean,
that might be like just like,
I mean it's not a diagnosis.
It is reference in the DSM 5,
but it's under the category of PTSD,
but in the ICD 11 it differs.
It's so fun.
Yes,
we can definitely talk about PC PTSD and
like to make it so fun for us.
Yeah, I mean,
I think it would be fun to have some just
exploratory sessions.
Definitely.
All right,
so let's definitely look into CPTSD,
migraines and chronic pain at the next
meeting.
Can anyone remember who was talking about
treating chronic pain in the last meeting
and making sure that they're on on this?
Anybody remember?
I can look it up.
And yeah, I was gonna say in the chat,
she just put it in the chat.
Ah, there you are.
Hi.
Do you think it's possible that Eileen
could we could send Eileen home with some
homework Exactly like, like,
like direct frontline,
like work that people are doing?
Yeah, they can do homework.
What do you need?
How do.
Like everything we everything we have on
pain management treatment protocols that
we can.
There's no way we can possibly do.
Yeah, there's mechanisms and yeah,
I can get you a consolidated report on it
for the next meeting if you'd like,
or before the next meeting.
Not me, I'm, I'm just like a nerd.
Yeah, just send it to medical psilocybin.
I just put in a chat.
Ian.
Cool, you got it.
Alrighty.
And then we can also go over that.
Perfect.
So I am actually very busy for the next
two weeks.
But how does the 25th sound for everyone?
Let me take a gander at our calendar here.
May 25th is Memorial Day, May 26th, 26th.
Think that should work at Still 9.
Sure.
Cool.
Right?
Yeah, that looks good.
Perfect.
Well, thank you everyone for coming.
I really appreciate all of your voices.
And to our newcomer, we welcome you back.
Please check out the department website
and see what other meetings we have.
I know training and education is on
Friday and the dosage is tomorrow.
They're working on preparation sessions,
integration sessions,
and other things at the next meeting,
so we look forward to seeing you more.
Thank you all for joining us today and
spending your Monday with us.
We really appreciate all of you and have
a great rest of your day.
Thank you everyone.